<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kszenes.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://kszenes.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-24T19:08:32+00:00</updated><id>https://kszenes.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">DuckDuckGo Bangs</title><link href="https://kszenes.github.io/blog/2024/DuckDuckGoBangs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DuckDuckGo Bangs"/><published>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kszenes.github.io/blog/2024/DuckDuckGoBangs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kszenes.github.io/blog/2024/DuckDuckGoBangs/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="problem-statement">Problem Statement</h1> <p>Nowadays, most of the time when I use a search engine, I usually know on which website I want to arrive on but I don’t the exact URL. For instance, if I want to learn more about the sinking of the Titanic, I would usually start by checking out the Wikipedia. Therefore, I would use “titanic wiki” as my search query and click on the first link (corresponding to the Wikipedia page). This process is pretty annoying, especially now that one needs to click through all the cookie menus on Google.</p> <h1 id="solution">Solution</h1> <p>Since this is how I use search engines 99% of the time, wouldn’t it be nice if I could directly search the website, in this case Wikipedia, for the query, in this case the Titanic. One of the coolest native features of DuckDuckGo, a privacy-centric search engine, which is lesser known (at least it was to me) is called DuckDuckGo bangs which enables precisely this. By starting a search query with a bang (an exclamation point) followed by a character code corresponding to the website and then the search query, DuckDuckGo directly issues the query to the website of interest and you are immediately redirected to the page you were looking for. In our previous example, one would need to use the character code <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">w</code> corresponding to Wikipedia:</p> <div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>!w titanic
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="available-bangs">Available Bangs</h2> <p>DuckDuckGo supports a huge number of websites (13’567 as of the time of writing this blog post) containing all the major websites and also lesser known ones. The list of available bangs can be viewed on their <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/bangs">website</a> and you can even make a suggestion if your website has not yet been added. In addition, if you use simply a bang plus your search query without the character code, DuckDuckGo redirects you to the first search result (reminiscent of the “I’m feeling lucky” feature of Google). I use this all the time for lesser known websites that have not been cataloged.</p> <h3 id="most-used-bangs">Most used bangs</h3> <p>Here are a list of my some of my most used bangs:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!</code>: I’m feeling lucky</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!w</code>: Wikipedia</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!gsc</code>: Google Scholar</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!gh</code>: GitHub</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!cpp</code>: Cpp Reference</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!pypi</code>: PyPi</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">!g</code>: Google</li> </ul> <h2 id="compatibility-with-other-search-engines">Compatibility with other search engines</h2> <p>Now you might say, this looks cool and all but I don’t want to switch my entire search engine to DuckDuckGo because the search results are not as good as Google. I would totally agree with. Actually, I use a search engine called StartPage which fetches results from Google without tracking everything you do on the internet. Does this mean you cannot benefit from this cool feature? There are a number of plugins for Firefox and Chromium-based web browsers which enable you to access this feature while still using your favorite search engine for default queries. The one that I am currently using is <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/banger/">Banger</a> for Firefox with which I am quite happy. However, there are a number of alternatives that are available by simply searching for “bangs” in the extension store.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDuckGo's hidden feature which will turbo-charge your web searching]]></summary></entry></feed>